<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Rants from the Ballmer Peak</title>
  <link href="https://gradha.github.io/" />
  <link href="https://gradha.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <id>https://gradha.github.io/</id>
  <generator>ipsumgenera</generator>
  <updated>2018-11-20T18:33:19Z</updated>
    <entry>
      <title>Package managers, the lazy alternative to git submodules</title>
      <link href="https://gradha.github.io/articles/2018/11/package-managers-the-lazy-alternative-to-git-submodules.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
      <id>https://gradha.github.io/articles/2018/11/package-managers-the-lazy-alternative-to-git-submodules.html</id>
      <published>2018-11-19T00:30:00Z</published>
      <updated>2018-11-20T18:32:00Z</updated>
      <author><name>Grzegorz Adam Hankiewicz</name></author>
      <content type="html">
&lt;h1&gt;Package managers, the lazy alternative to git submodules&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;h2&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.idol-grapher.com/2099"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../i/lazy_developers.jpg" alt="I'm not lazy, I'm just saving my energy" style="width:100%;max-width:600px" align="right" hspace="8pt" vspace="8pt" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p&gt;Package managers have always looked strange to me. Why would you &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;want&lt;/span&gt; to use one?  It is actually not weird to have that point of view, especially if your background comes from programming languages like C or C++, which don't have any well known package manager (&lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/a/36023212/172690"&gt;even though people keep trying to build some&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/cpp/comments/3d1vjq/is_there_a_c_package_manager_if_not_how_do_you/"&gt;developers resort to using the system libraries/packages or git submodules to manage their software builds&lt;/a&gt;. On the other hand, people mostly coming from interpreted languages are so used to the idea that &lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; using a package manager seems like crazy advice. Today, software development uses some form of source content management, and it seems like &lt;a href="https://git-scm.com"&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; has &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;won the war&lt;/span&gt;, especially since it is used by &lt;a href="https://github.com"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, possibly the most popular free repository choice for open source and free software. As such, many de...&lt;/p&gt;1484 bytes out of 31695.</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Prototyping a dumb server for location sharing apps</title>
      <link href="https://gradha.github.io/articles/2018/04/prototyping-a-dumb-server-for-location-sharing-apps.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
      <id>https://gradha.github.io/articles/2018/04/prototyping-a-dumb-server-for-location-sharing-apps.html</id>
      <published>2018-04-01T01:27:00Z</published>
      <updated>2018-07-27T00:26:00Z</updated>
      <author><name>Grzegorz Adam Hankiewicz</name></author>
      <content type="html">
&lt;h1&gt;Prototyping a dumb server for location sharing apps&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div style="background-color:yellow;float:right;margin:1px"&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/p4tLL59NtZc?t=51"&gt;&lt;video autoplay="autoplay" muted="muted" loop="loop" style="width: 166px; height: 166px;"&gt; &lt;source src="../../../i/omb_01.mp4" type="video/mp4"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../i/omb_01.gif" width="166" height="166" /&gt;&lt;/source&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the year 2009 Google created &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_Latitude"&gt;Google Latitude&lt;/a&gt;, which was a service to report your own mobile location to their servers so that other users could see where you are. It is funny to me that I didn't even know such a thing existed until 2010, when one of my previous coworkers released &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101027221033/http://www.latitudie.com/"&gt;Latitudie&lt;/a&gt;, which was an iOS app using Google's Latitude service (I even did buy it and use it for my nefarious purposes!). But you had to wait until the end of 2011 (&lt;a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2011/04/how-apple-tracks-your-location-without-your-consent-and-why-it-matters/"&gt;after possibly the most public false start&lt;/a&gt;) for &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Find_My_Friends"&gt;Apple to innovate with their Find My Friends app&lt;/a&gt;, offering pretty much the same service as Google, except for the fact that you were limited to using Apple devices and, at least at that time, there was no way to view a friend's location on a desktop web browser. Those l...&lt;/p&gt;1521 bytes out of 41257.</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Chromecast without internet is the Shitcast</title>
      <link href="https://gradha.github.io/articles/2017/07/chromecast-without-internet-is-the-shitcast.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
      <id>https://gradha.github.io/articles/2017/07/chromecast-without-internet-is-the-shitcast.html</id>
      <published>2017-07-20T19:12:00Z</published>
      <updated>2017-07-20T21:00:00Z</updated>
      <author><name>Grzegorz Adam Hankiewicz</name></author>
      <content type="html">
&lt;h1&gt;Chromecast without internet is the Shitcast&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;Summer is one of those times of the year technical savvy people need to step away from their usual hardware devices or face being labelled geeks, nerds, autists, aspergers, freaks, or whatever the hip word is among the non technical people. Writing software on the computer or teaching yourself new stuff at home is bad. On the other hand, risking skin cancer and cirrhosis at the beach while forwarding stale memes with privative messaging apps is cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.idol-grapher.com/2052"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../i/shitcast_summer.jpg" alt="Summer? They'll force me to dance nearly naked in front of fat, ugly, smelly virgins. Again." style="width:100%;max-width:600px" align="right" hspace="8pt" vspace="8pt" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p&gt;Visiting my parents far away from civilization for a week I wanted to test this thingy called &lt;a href="http://chromecast.com/"&gt;Chromecast&lt;/a&gt;, sold by &lt;a href="http://lmgtfy.com/?q=google"&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt; in supermarkets. It's a cheap computer/Android streaming receiver you connect to a screen. My parents like watching low quality videos of old memes sent through &lt;a href="http://www.whatsapp.com"&gt;WhatsApp&lt;/a&gt;, but prefer to do so on a big screen rather than their small phones, so I thought of bringing it along some downloaded stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The experiment&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course I tested the Chromecast first at home. The setup went really smooth, and even when I tried to switch WiFi networks or i...&lt;/p&gt;1483 bytes out of 12506.</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Apple's Core Data greatest feature: brainwashing</title>
      <link href="https://gradha.github.io/articles/2017/05/apples-core-data-greatest-feature-brainwashing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
      <id>https://gradha.github.io/articles/2017/05/apples-core-data-greatest-feature-brainwashing.html</id>
      <published>2017-05-28T09:45:00Z</published>
      <updated>2017-05-28T09:45:00Z</updated>
      <author><name>Grzegorz Adam Hankiewicz</name></author>
      <content type="html">
&lt;h1&gt;Apple's Core Data greatest feature: brainwashing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.idol-grapher.com/1695"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../i/core_data_pretty.jpg" alt="Core Data, pretty on the outside, but painful once you use it" style="width:100%;max-width:600px" align="right" hspace="8pt" vspace="8pt" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now that another project is ending for me, it's always a good idea to review the good and bad things, a postmortem. This time, thanks to Sir Arthur's Legacy from Crazy Hipster Land (you know who you are!) I got to deal with Apple's Core Data &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;yet&lt;/span&gt; another time, for a project which didn't really need it. Thanks to Apple being idiots, it's never possible to hard link any kind of their documentation with confidence because it seems to move every year with each new SDK update, so I have now the &lt;a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/content/documentation/Cocoa/Conceptual/CoreData/index.html"&gt;following documentation link&lt;/a&gt; in case you don't know what Core Data is, but who knows for how long it will last. Your best chance is to Google &amp;quot;Apple's Core Data&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, just like any tool, framework, library, etc, you can use stuff just for the sake of it even if you don't need it. And sometimes the use can be justified through external reasons, like using a &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;lesser&lt;/span&gt; programming language because it is easier to find programmers for your team. But regardless of justification, C...&lt;/p&gt;1484 bytes out of 18636.</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Static vs dynamic linking is the wrong discussion</title>
      <link href="https://gradha.github.io/articles/2016/12/static-vs-dynamic-linking-is-the-wrong-discussion.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
      <id>https://gradha.github.io/articles/2016/12/static-vs-dynamic-linking-is-the-wrong-discussion.html</id>
      <published>2016-12-26T09:41:00Z</published>
      <updated>2016-12-26T09:41:00Z</updated>
      <author><name>Grzegorz Adam Hankiewicz</name></author>
      <content type="html">
&lt;h1&gt;Static vs dynamic linking is the wrong discussion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.idol-grapher.com/1977"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../i/static_things.jpg" alt="I've seen things, thing you wouldn't believe" style="width:100%;max-width:600px" align="right" hspace="8pt" vspace="8pt" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p&gt;The developer &lt;a href="http://catb.org/jargon/html/H/holy-wars.html"&gt;holy war&lt;/a&gt; between static and dynamic linking continues to threaten our peace. Missiles in favour of &lt;a href="https://www.akkadia.org/drepper/no_static_linking.html"&gt;dynamic linking&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://sta.li/faq"&gt;static linking&lt;/a&gt; won't allow us to sleep at night, with debris &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/learnprogramming/comments/4bo951/eli5_this_whole_fiasco_with_javascript_node_and/"&gt;reaching unexpected areas&lt;/a&gt; previously thought to be safe. When my own zealotry was at an all high I wrote that &lt;a href="https://gradha.github.io/articles/2016/12/../../2013/08/users-prefer-static-linking.html"&gt;Users prefer static linking&lt;/a&gt;, but the wounds of war have opened my eyes and I need no more cripples among my friends and family to understand that we are all wrong and should make peace. Static linking needs to be banished from our lands, or maybe upgraded into a new concept, but in any case we need to unite and fight against the true source of our despair: operating systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Useless options&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The main reason developers still argue about static or dynamic linking is because that's as far as thei...&lt;/p&gt;1484 bytes out of 11096.</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Patterns as solution anti-patterns</title>
      <link href="https://gradha.github.io/articles/2016/06/patterns-as-solution-antipatterns.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
      <id>https://gradha.github.io/articles/2016/06/patterns-as-solution-antipatterns.html</id>
      <published>2016-06-23T22:51:00Z</published>
      <updated>2016-06-23T22:51:00Z</updated>
      <author><name>Grzegorz Adam Hankiewicz</name></author>
      <content type="html">
&lt;h1&gt;Patterns as solution anti-patterns&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;a href="http://antikpopfangirl.blogspot.com.es/2016/06/the-kpopalypse-guide-to-university-life.html"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../i/patterns_university_iu.jpg" alt="Unfortunately I'm stupidier than IU" style="width:100%;max-width:460px" align="right" hspace="8pt" vspace="8pt" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don't remember the exact time I &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;crashed&lt;/span&gt; against software design patterns. Most likely it was my university days, most of the stuff I learnt there I hated with a passion. But since &lt;a href="http://arcadey.net/2015/05/netizens-finally-start-to-realize-that-they-were-wrong-about-t-aras-bullying-scandal/"&gt;you can't hate forever&lt;/a&gt;, slowly the hate turned into apathy, and at least I stopped trying to run away from them. Recent &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/t1_Pw563opc?t=35"&gt;directives&lt;/a&gt; at my current workplace have reminded me of patterns, but now I've tried to understand what drove me crazy about patterns. What makes patterns so vilified by some, or followed blindly by others like a &lt;a href="https://www.java.com/"&gt;religion&lt;/a&gt;? Is there something we can do to avoid the bickering? Are patterns bad per se, good, or neutral? Is it us who wield them incorrectly? If you are bored enough and want to waste your time, follow me along this public introspection. Otherwise my TL;DR for you is patterns can't be taught at will and making them a requirement for software development is usually a bad idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;B...&lt;/h2&gt;1485 bytes out of 20141.</content>
    </entry>
</feed>