<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Rants from the Ballmer Peak</title>
  <link href="https://gradha.github.io/" />
  <link href="https://gradha.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <id>https://gradha.github.io/</id>
  <generator>ipsumgenera</generator>
  <updated>2021-05-31T10:29:24Z</updated>
    <entry>
      <title>Jetbrains backs off on Kotlin/Native memory model, Android devs too stupid to learn new tricks</title>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gradha.github.io/articles/2021/05/jetbrains-backs-off-on-kotlinnative-memory-model-android-devs-too-stupid-to-learn-new-tricks.html" />
      <id>https://gradha.github.io/articles/2021/05/jetbrains-backs-off-on-kotlinnative-memory-model-android-devs-too-stupid-to-learn-new-tricks.html</id>
      <published>2021-05-30T19:28:00Z</published>
      <updated>2021-05-31T11:29:00Z</updated>
      <author><name>Grzegorz Adam Hankiewicz</name></author>
      <content type="html">
&lt;h1&gt;Jetbrains backs off on Kotlin/Native memory model, Android devs too stupid to learn new tricks&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now that &lt;a href="https://events.google.com/io/"&gt;Google IO 2021&lt;/a&gt; is behind our backs and it essentially boiled down to refining existing libs, &lt;a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2021/05/google-shows-off-android-12s-huge-ui-overhaul/"&gt;fresh coat of paint&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://android-developers.googleblog.com/2021/05/android-security-and-privacy-recap.html"&gt;copying Apple Privacy policies&lt;/a&gt;, the most shocking revelation to me was &lt;a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/kotlin/2021/05/kotlin-native-memory-management-update/"&gt;Jetbrains update on the Kotlin/Native memory model&lt;/a&gt; which dropped like a bomb:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;TL;DR: The original Kotlin/Native memory management approach was very easy to implement, but it created a host of problems for developers trying to share their Kotlin code between different platforms.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course this reversal is hidden among piles of marketing speech, but is happily pointed out by the comments, where Roman Elizarov can't say much other than, &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;"yeah, we will make that work"&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;needed&lt;/span&gt; change comes a bit too late to the party, because most Android developers with an interest in Kotlin/Native have probably already touched the big pile of poo that Kotlin/Native memory model ...&lt;/p&gt;8 bytes out of 20318.</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Machine learning is killing Dropbox search</title>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gradha.github.io/articles/2019/05/machine-learning-is-killing-dropbox-search.html" />
      <id>https://gradha.github.io/articles/2019/05/machine-learning-is-killing-dropbox-search.html</id>
      <published>2019-05-04T19:50:00Z</published>
      <updated>2019-05-08T00:19:00Z</updated>
      <author><name>Grzegorz Adam Hankiewicz</name></author>
      <content type="html">
&lt;h1&gt;Machine learning is killing Dropbox search&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;a href="https://toodur2.tistory.com/1938"&gt;&lt;img align="right" alt="A webapp in Nim? What is he smoking? Is that possible at all?" hspace="8pt" src="../../../i/dropbox_searching.jpg" style="width:100%;max-width:600px" vspace="8pt"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Waking up with your left foot&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently the &lt;a href="https://blogs.dropbox.com/tech/"&gt;Dropbox Tech Blog&lt;/a&gt; published one article titled &lt;a href="https://blogs.dropbox.com/tech/2019/05/content-suggestions-machine-learning/"&gt;Using machine learning to predict what file you need next&lt;/a&gt; which ended ticking me off. The reason is simple, Dropbox search feature stopped working for me about two years ago. Unfortunately I'm used to dozens of products having bugs that make them inconvenient, and you simply learn to live with crap because fixing it is more expensive than ignoring it. As a programmer you learn that software is far from being the product of a single person, and groups of different people have different views on what quality is, means, or how it is achieved. We are all slaves to the financial aspect of business anyway, and we know the business side doesn't really care about bugs unless they torpedo their income, so priorities tend to be somewhere else (shiny new features! Shinyyyyyyy!). So seeing the Dropbox blog gloat about how awesome machine learning is finally prompted me to make public how crap their search actually is, and has been for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&amp;lt;p...7 bytes out of 12476.</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>From Python windows console to Nim Karax webapp</title>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gradha.github.io/articles/2019/03/from-python-windows-console-to-nim-karax-webapp.html" />
      <id>https://gradha.github.io/articles/2019/03/from-python-windows-console-to-nim-karax-webapp.html</id>
      <published>2019-03-26T20:58:00Z</published>
      <updated>2019-06-26T20:58:00Z</updated>
      <author><name>Grzegorz Adam Hankiewicz</name></author>
      <content type="html">
&lt;h1&gt;From Python windows console to Nim Karax webapp&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;h2&gt;A challenger appears&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;a href="https://locomotion1020.tistory.com/18"&gt;&lt;img align="right" alt="A webapp in Nim? What is he smoking? Is that possible at all?" hspace="8pt" src="../../../i/webapp_nim_wat.jpg" style="width:100%;max-width:600px" vspace="8pt"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p&gt;Between people who really love programming and those who treat technology like inscrutable magic there are those like Kpopalypse who are capable of building software without being dedicated programmers. If you go to &lt;a href="https://kpopalypse.com/"&gt;Kpopalypse's website&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://kpopalypse.com/2014/01/20/kpopalypse-faq/"&gt;click on Sully&lt;/a&gt; you will find out many facts about his persona, but you will miss that he has released &lt;a href="https://kpopalypse.com/2018/10/19/stan-loona-or-else/"&gt;sp00ky interactive Halloween fanfiction&lt;/a&gt; or adventure games like &lt;a href="https://kpopalypse.com/2019/01/24/escape-from-the-idol-dungeon-an-adventure-game-by-kpopalypse/"&gt;Escape from the Idol Dungeon&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://kpopalypse.com"&gt;Try Not To Have Gay Sex With Yves&lt;/a&gt;, showing higher than average levels of determination to understand and dominate technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most recently Kpopalypse released a &lt;a href="https://kpopalypse.com/2019/02/24/the-kpopalypse-fan-comment-generator/"&gt;fan comment generator&lt;/a&gt;, which allows anybody with a Windows computer to mechanize the act of answering posts in crazy kpop forums. The orig...&lt;/p&gt;8 bytes out of 24032.</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Package managers, the lazy alternative to git submodules</title>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gradha.github.io/articles/2018/11/package-managers-the-lazy-alternative-to-git-submodules.html" />
      <id>https://gradha.github.io/articles/2018/11/package-managers-the-lazy-alternative-to-git-submodules.html</id>
      <published>2018-11-19T00:30:00Z</published>
      <updated>2018-11-26T18:31:00Z</updated>
      <author><name>Grzegorz Adam Hankiewicz</name></author>
      <content type="html">
&lt;h1&gt;Package managers, the lazy alternative to git submodules&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;h2&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.idol-grapher.com/2099"&gt;&lt;img align="right" alt="I'm not lazy, I'm just saving my energy" hspace="8pt" src="../../../i/lazy_developers.jpg" style="width:100%;max-width:600px" vspace="8pt"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p&gt;Package managers have always looked strange to me. Why would you &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;want&lt;/span&gt; to use one?  It is actually not weird to have that point of view, especially if your background comes from programming languages like C or C++, which don't have any well known package manager (&lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/a/36023212/172690"&gt;even though people keep trying to build some&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/cpp/comments/3d1vjq/is_there_a_c_package_manager_if_not_how_do_you/"&gt;developers resort to using the system libraries/packages or git submodules to manage their software builds&lt;/a&gt;. On the other hand, people mostly coming from interpreted languages are so used to the idea that &lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; using a package manager seems like crazy advice. Today, software development uses some form of source content management, and it seems like &lt;a href="https://git-scm.com"&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; has &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;won the war&lt;/span&gt;, especially since it is used by &lt;a href="https://github.com"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, possibly the most popular free repository choice for open source and free software. As such, many de...&lt;/p&gt;6 bytes out of 31726.</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Prototyping a dumb server for location sharing apps</title>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gradha.github.io/articles/2018/04/prototyping-a-dumb-server-for-location-sharing-apps.html" />
      <id>https://gradha.github.io/articles/2018/04/prototyping-a-dumb-server-for-location-sharing-apps.html</id>
      <published>2018-04-01T01:27:00Z</published>
      <updated>2018-07-27T00:26:00Z</updated>
      <author><name>Grzegorz Adam Hankiewicz</name></author>
      <content type="html">
&lt;h1&gt;Prototyping a dumb server for location sharing apps&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div style="background-color:yellow;float:right;margin:1px"&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/p4tLL59NtZc?t=51"&gt;&lt;video autoplay="" loop="" muted="" playsinline="" style="width: 166px; height: 166px;"&gt; &lt;source src="../../../i/omb_01.mp4" type="video/mp4"/&gt;&lt;img height="166" src="../../../i/omb_01.gif" width="166"/&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the year 2009 Google created &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_Latitude"&gt;Google Latitude&lt;/a&gt;, which was a service to report your own mobile location to their servers so that other users could see where you are. It is funny to me that I didn't even know such a thing existed until 2010, when one of my previous coworkers released &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101027221033/http://www.latitudie.com/"&gt;Latitudie&lt;/a&gt;, which was an iOS app using Google's Latitude service (I even did buy it and use it for my nefarious purposes!). But you had to wait until the end of 2011 (&lt;a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2011/04/how-apple-tracks-your-location-without-your-consent-and-why-it-matters/"&gt;after possibly the most public false start&lt;/a&gt;) for &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Find_My_Friends"&gt;Apple to innovate with their Find My Friends app&lt;/a&gt;, offering pretty much the same service as Google, except for the fact that you were limited to using Apple devices and, at least at that time, there was no way to view a friend's location on a desktop web brow...&lt;/p&gt;5 bytes out of 41557.</content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Chromecast without internet is the Shitcast</title>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gradha.github.io/articles/2017/07/chromecast-without-internet-is-the-shitcast.html" />
      <id>https://gradha.github.io/articles/2017/07/chromecast-without-internet-is-the-shitcast.html</id>
      <published>2017-07-20T19:12:00Z</published>
      <updated>2017-07-20T21:00:00Z</updated>
      <author><name>Grzegorz Adam Hankiewicz</name></author>
      <content type="html">
&lt;h1&gt;Chromecast without internet is the Shitcast&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;Summer is one of those times of the year technical savvy people need to step away from their usual hardware devices or face being labelled geeks, nerds, autists, aspergers, freaks, or whatever the hip word is among the non technical people. Writing software on the computer or teaching yourself new stuff at home is bad. On the other hand, risking skin cancer and cirrhosis at the beach while forwarding stale memes with privative messaging apps is cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.idol-grapher.com/2052"&gt;&lt;img align="right" alt="Summer? They'll force me to dance nearly naked in front of fat, ugly, smelly virgins. Again." hspace="8pt" src="../../../i/shitcast_summer.jpg" style="width:100%;max-width:600px" vspace="8pt"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p&gt;Visiting my parents far away from civilization for a week I wanted to test this thingy called &lt;a href="http://chromecast.com/"&gt;Chromecast&lt;/a&gt;, sold by &lt;a href="http://lmgtfy.com/?q=google"&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt; in supermarkets. It's a cheap computer/Android streaming receiver you connect to a screen. My parents like watching low quality videos of old memes sent through &lt;a href="http://www.whatsapp.com"&gt;WhatsApp&lt;/a&gt;, but prefer to do so on a big screen rather than their small phones, so I thought of bringing it along some downloaded stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The experiment&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course I tested the Chromecast first at home. The setup went really smooth, and even when I tried to switch WiFi networks or i...&lt;/p&gt;9 bytes out of 12506.</content>
    </entry>
</feed>
